So good, so we can finally get underway, so
this is CS 6700 reinforcement learning, if
anyone is here by mistake looking for the
planning class still well you should leave
okay, and yeah so how many of you were in
the machine learning course just for me to
get a sense okay large fraction of the people
were in ML okay and so, this is a very the
different kind of learning than what we have
looked at it in ML right, So in machine learning
we looked at familiar modes of machine learning
where the idea was to learn from data, you
know so you were given lot of data as training
instances for you and essentially we're trying
to learn from those training instances as
to what to do right.
And there were different kinds of problems
that we were looking at, so one was supervised
learning problem in which you are looking
at classification and regression, oh yeah
so in the machine learning class we looked
at learning from data right primarily so one
of the models we looked at was supervised
learning right where we learnt about classification
and regression the goal there was to learn
a mapping from an input space to a output
which could be a categorical output in which
case its classification it could be a continuous
output in which case it was called regression
right.
So if you haven't been in the ML class don't
worry about it right because this is just
to tell you that RL is not whatever you learnt
in the ML class okay.
So if you haven't learnt anything in the ML
class then you don't have anything to unlearn.
So don't worry so the second second kind of
learning thing we looked at was unsupervised
learning where there was really no output
that was expected of you right since therefore
there was no supervision the goal was to find
patterns in the input data.
I will give you lot of data points.
Can you find out if there are groupings of
similar kinds of data points can I divide
them into segments right.
So that kind of a thing was called clustering,
right or you are asked to figure out if there
were frequently repeating patterns in the
data right and so this is called frequent
pattern mining or derived problem there was
Association rule mining and so on so forth
right so people have heard me give this analogy
multiple, multiple times before but this is
the most apt one how did you learn to cycle,
right.
so was it supervised learning so how did you
learn to cycle, somebody who hasn't heard
me or then who hasn't been in ML, you haven't
been in ML right yeah okay, how did you learn
to cycle, was did somebody tell you how to
cycle and then you just followed their instruction?
Okay first of all do you know how to cycle,
Yes.
Do you know how to cycle, yeah you, Yes.
Okay how did you learn to cycle fell down
a couple of times and that automatically made
you cycle, you have to actually figure out
how to not to fall down, right.
So falling down alone is not enough but you
have to try different things right it's not
supervised learning is really not supervised
learning how much ever you think because,
now that I have given this talk multiple times
people are getting wise to it, right earlier
when I used to ask these people used to say
of course it’s supervised learning my uncle
was there holding me or my father was telling
me what to do and so on so forth.
At best what did they tell you, hey look out
look out don't fall down, right.
So that doesn't count as supervision, so or
keep your body right keep your body up or
something some kind of very vague instructions
was what they were giving you right, supervised
learning would mean that so you get on the
cycle somebody tells you okay, now push down
with your left foot with three pounds of pressure
right and move your center of gravity three
degrees to the right, right.
So this is I mean somebody has to give you
exactly what is the control signals that you
had to give to your body in order for you
to cycle right, then that would be supervised
learning right.
If somebody actually gives you supervision
at that scale you would probably have never
learned to cycle if we think about it because
it's such a complex, complex dynamical system
if somebody gives you control at that level
gives you input at that level you will never
learn to cycle.
And so immediately people flip and say that
it was unsupervised learning right, because
yeah of course nobody told me how to cycle
therefore it is unsupervised learning.
So if it is truly unsupervised learning what
should have happened is you should have watched
hundreds of videos of people cycling figure
out what is the pattern of cycling that they
do okay, and get on a cycle and reproduce
it right?
So that is essentially what unsupervised learning
would be you just have lot of data right and
based on the data you figure out what the
patterns are and then you try to execute those
patterns that does not work right, you can
watch hours and hours of somebody playing
flight simulator you cannot go and fly a plane
right, so you have to get on the cycle yourself
and you have to try things yourself right
so that's the crux here right.
So what it's how did you learn to cycle is
neither of the above right is neither supervised
nor unsupervised.
It's a it's a different paradigm right.
So the reason I always start out my talks
not just in the class but in general when
I talk about reinforcement learning is because
people will always talk about reinforcement
learning as unsupervised learning and it's
always really irks me because it's not an
unsupervised learning just because you don't
have a classification error or a class label
doesn't make it unsupervised learning it is
a completely different form of learning and
so reinforcement learning is essentially this
mathematical formalism for this trial and
error kind of learning right.
So how do you learn from this kind of minimal
feedback you know, falling down hurts or somebody
your mom or somebody stands there and claps,
when you finally managed to get on the cycle
you know that's kind of a positive reinforcement.
Where if you fall down you get hurt right,
that's kind of a negative feedback how do
you just use this kinds of minimal feedback
and you learn to cycle, so this is essentially
the crux of what reinforcement learning is
about trial and error right.
So the goal here is to learn about a system
through interacting with the system right.
It's not something that is done completely
offline okay you have some notion of interaction
with the system okay and you learn about the
system through that interaction.
Reinforcement learning originally was inspired
by behavioral psychology right.
So one of the earliest reinforcement systems
that was studied was a Pavlov's dog, how many
of you know of the Pavlov's dog experiment?
what is the Pavlov's dog experiment?
in association with whenever he's going to
do okay, so whenever like he just utterly
need above the dog started expecting the food
and started salivating yeah so that is called
a conditioned reflex, so when the dog looks
at the food and starts salivating it is a
primary response because there is a reason
for it to salivate on the sight of food any
idea why?
Exactly so it is preparing to digest the food
you know when you show the food it is preparing
to digest the food so it starts salivating
right.
So then now if you think about it right hearing
the bell and it salivates what is it doing
preparing to digest a bell?
So when you ring the bell and then serve the
food the dog forms an association between
the bell and the food right and later on when
you just ring the bell without even serving
the food the dog starts salivating in response
to digesting the food that it expects to be
delivered right so it essentially the food
is the payoff you know the food is like a
reward for it and it has learned to form associations
between signals in this case which was a bell
like the input signal which was the bell and
the reward that is going to get right.
So this was called behavioral conditioning
right and so inspired by these kinds of experiments
and more complex behavioral experiments on
animals people started to come up with different
theories to explain how learning proceeds
right.
In fact some of the earlier reinforcement
learning papers appeared in behavioral psychology
journals right, the earliest paper by Sutton
and Barto appeared in brain and behavioral
sciences Journal, just go back I needed to
need to say something about Sutton and Barto
know that there's a larger audience you can
tell that what then so the we're going to
follow a textbook written by Rich Sutton and
Andrew Barto right but more importantly they
are also kind of the co-founders of the modern
field of reinforcement learning right.
So in 1983 they wrote a paper adaptive neuron
like element that learn control behavior or
something to that effect right and that essentially
kickstarted the whole modern field of reinforcement
learning.
So the concept of reinforcement learning like
I said goes back to Pavlov and earlier right,
people have been talking about these kind
of behavioral conditioning and learning and
stuff, but the whole modern computational
techniques that people use in reinforcement
learning are started by Sutton and Barto right.
So what is reinforcement learning right, so
it's learning about stimuli right the inputs
that are coming to you and the actions that
you can take in response to it right, learning
about the stimuli only from rewards and punishments
so you're not going to get anything else food
is a reward right falling down and scraping
your hand that's a punishment, right.
So only from these kinds of rewards and punishments
alone right, there is no detailed supervision
available nobody tells you what is the response
that you should give to a specific input right,
suppose you are playing a game there are multiple
ways in which you can learn to play a game
right so you can learn to play chess by looking
at a board position right and then looking
at a table that tells you for this board position
this is the move you have to make right and
then you go and make the move alright.
So that is a kind of supervision that you
could get you know that gives you a kind of
a mapping from the input to the output right,
it gives you a mapping from the input to the
output and essentially you learn to generalize
from that.
So this is what we mean by detailed supervision
so, another way of learning to play chess
is just you have an opponent sit in front
of him and you just make a sequence of moves
at the end of the move if you win okay, you
get a reward somebody pays you say 10 rupees,
okay if you lose you have to pay the opponent
ten rupees that's all, that is all that happens
thats all the feedback you’re going to get
right, whether you are going to get the 10
rupees or going to lose the 10 rupees at the
end of the game so nobody tells you given
this position this is the move you should
have made that is what we mean by saying learning
from rewards and punishments in the absence
of detailed supervision okay is that clear
okay?
And a crucial component to this is trial and
error learning because since I do not know
what is the right thing to do given an input
right I need to try multiple things to see
what the outcome will be right, I need to
try different things to see if I am going
to get the reward or not right if I do not
try different things, I am not going to be
able to learn anything at all right.
So we will I can give you more formal mathematical
reasons for why we need all of this as we
let go on but this is intuitively you can
understand this as requiring exploration so,
that you know what the right outcome is right.
And there are a bunch of things which are
also characteristic of reinforcement learning
problems one of those is that the outcomes
right the pai the rewards and punishments
based on which you are learning can be fairly
delayed in time they need not be temporally
close to the thing that cost it, I mean while
you are playing a game let us say right, so
you might you know drop a batsman right and
then he goes on to score like 150 or something
like that right so then you lose the match
at the end of the day right but the event
that cost you to lose the match is the dropped
catch that probably happened around the 12th
over right, or it could be much more convoluted
causal cause and effect right so and how many
of you follow cricket?
My god really losing popularity yeah, put
your hands down, I am not going to give a
cricket example then forget it okay so there
are a bunch of other things right so, so we
talked about delayed rewards the rewards could
come much later in time from the action that
cost the reward to happen right for example,
let us go back to our cycling case right I
might have done something stupid or I might
have gone over a stone somewhere right, while
I am cycling at a very high speed there might
have been a small stone in the road and that
that will cause me to lose my balance right.
And then I will try my level best to get the
balance back right I might not and I will
finally fall down and get hurt that does not
mean what caused the falling down is the last
action I tried right, I might have desperately
tried to jump off the cycle or something like
that but that is not what caused the punishment
right, the what caused the punishment happened
a few seconds ago when I ran over the stone,
right.
So there could be this kind of a temporal
disconnect between what causes the reward
or punishment from the actual reward and punishment
so it becomes a little tricky how do you are
going to learn those things right learn the
associations right.
So quite often right you are going to need
a sequence of actions to obtain a reward it
is not going to be like a one-shot thing right
you are going to need a sequence of actions
to get to the reward, so again going back
to the chess example right, you are not going
to get a reward every time you move a piece
on the board right, you have to finish playing
the game at the end of the game if you actually
manage to win you get a reward so, its a sequence
of actions right.
And therefore you need to learn some kind
of an association between the inputs that
you are seeing in this case it will be the
board positions right or how fast the cycle
is moving and how unbalanced do you feel and
so on so forth right to actions so the inputs
that you are getting which sometimes which
we will call states right and the actions
that you take in response to this input that
you are seeing right.
So this is essentially what you are going
to be doing when you are solving a reinforcement
learning problem.
So this kind of associations are essentially
known as policies right, so what you are essentially
learning is a policy to behave in a world,
right.
So you are learning a policy to play chess
or you are learning a policy to cycle right
so this is essentially what you are learning
right you are not just learning about individual
actions right, and all of this happen typically
in a noisy stochastic world okay that the
makes things more challenging, so these are
all the different characteristics of reinforcement
learning problems right and I will be looking
at all of this as we go along right in when
this I will not be explicitly talking about
each and every one of these bullet points
but everything that we look at all the algorithms
all the methods that we look at as we go along
in this course okay, we will have all these
aspects as part of it okay.
So reinforcement learning has been used fairly
successfully in a wide variety of applications
right, so you can see a helicopter there okay,
so that is not a cut and paste error the helicopter
is actually flying upside down okay, so the
this group at Stanford and Berkeley which
have actually used reinforcement learning
to train a helicopter to fly all kinds of
things not just upside down an an RL agent
can do all kinds of tricks on the helicopter
so, I will show you a video in a minute and
it is an amazing piece of work right I mean
it's considered it was considered the showpiece
application for reinforcement learning getting
such a complex control system to work and
it actually could do things at a much finer
levels of control than a human being could.
Well that’s after all a machine so we would
expect that but the tricky part was how it
learned to control this complex system from
without any human intervention right, and
in the middle right so they I have a couple
of games there so that is can you see that
is too small an arrow that is a game called
backgammon right so how many of you know about
backgammon, 1, 2 plus one maybe.
How many of you know about Ludo?
Okay fine so backgammon is like a two player
ludo okay so you throw the dice you move pieces
around and you take them off the board right,
so it is a fairly easy game but then you have
all kinds of strategies that you could do
with it but it is also a hard game for computers
to play because of the stochasticity right
and also because of a large branching factor
that is there in the game, so at each point
there are many many combinations in which
you could move the board pieces around and
then there is this die role that adds an additional
complexity.
So people are not really you know getting
great results and then there is this person
Jerry Tesaro from IBM who came up with something
called neuro gammon think it was called neuro
gammon and that was trained using supervised
learning and a neural network and, so if it
had if he had done it recently it would have
been called a deep learning version of neuro
gammon or something because he did it back
in the 90s early 90s it was just called neural
network version of backgammon and it played
really well for a computer program right so
it was essentially the best computer program
backgammon player at that point.
And then Jerry heard about TD heard about
reinforcement learning he decided to train
a reinforcement learning agent to play backgammon
so what he did was set up this reinforcement
learning agent which played against another
copy of itself, let them play hundreds and
hundreds of games rather thousands and thousands
of games so essentially what they did was
so you train one copy for like 100 move 100
games or something then you move it here right
freeze it and then continue learning with
this.
So essentially what was happening as you learn
you are playing against better and better
players gradually your opponent was also improving
right.
And then so this was called self play right,
so he trained the backgammon using self play
and it came to a point where they TD gammon
as he called it was even better than the human
player of backgammon at that point in the
world right so they actually had head-to-head
challenge with the human champion there is
a world championship of backgammon you know
it is apparently very popular in the Middle
East and people actually have World Championships
that's the world championship of backgammon
and so, he challenged the human champion which
IBM seems to do a lot right I mean they challenged
Kasparov to matches and things like this so,
he also challenged Tesauro works for IBM.
You should realize right people who spend
a lot of resources getting computers to play
games, will probably be working for IBM so,
Jerry had this thing and it beat the world
champion so we have reinforcement learning
agent that is the best backgammon player in
the world not no more best computer player
or anything right so we could actually make
that claim right and there's another game
there this is a snapshot from the game of
Go right so people have played go? oh come
on if that leaves one or two people who have
played go okay, people have played othello
okay that's also a very few number isn't it
one of those free games on ubuntu I thought
everybody plays that because I mean at some
point or other well you would rather play
Othello than watch paint dry you know.
But anyway so goes goes a like a more complex
version of Othello if you would right it is
again a very hard game for computers to play
because the branching factor is huge right
and it is actually a miracle that humans even
play this because the search trees and other
things that is really complex right so this
is 1 case which clearly illustrates that humans
actually solve problems in a fundamentally
different way than we try to write down in
our algorithms because, we seem to be making
all kinds of intuitive leaps in order to be
able to play go right.
So there's this person David silver who currently
works for Google deep mind and but before
that he spent some time with Jerry Tesauro
at IBM and at some point along the way he
came up with this reinforcement learning agent
called the TD search that plays go at a decent
level its still not, not like master human
level performance but it performs plays at
a pretty decent level ok so he what I am pointing
out here is things that are typically hard
for traditional computer algorithms or even
traditional machine learning approaches to
solve AI has had good success right.
And here is another example of them to point
should I use this or that I forget which one
right, they told me I should use only one
of those screens for pointing because it is
hard for them to record on the other one I
forget which one okay, forget it there are
some robots on the bottom left of the screen
right and so that is a snapshot from the UT
Austin Robo soccer team called Austin Villa
right, and they use reinforcement learning
to get their robots to execute really complex
strategies so this is really cool.
But the nice thing about the Robo socket application
is that they don't use reinforcement learning
alone right they actually use a mix of different
learning strategies and also planning and
so on so forth, which is going on in the other
studio right so they use a mix of different
kinds of AI and machine learning techniques
in order to get a very very competent agent
which is very hard to beat and they have been
the Champions I think two or three years running
now in the humanoid league right.
And again hard control problems things like
how do I take a spot-kick, you know those
were the things for which they used reinforcement
learning which is a really hard balancing
problems basically we have to balance the
robot on one leg and then swing the other
leg so that you can take the kick and it turns
out to be a hard control problem right.
So they used RL to RL to solve those right
and then up on the top right ok is an application
which will probably the one that actually
makes money of all these three all the others
right that is on essentially on using reinforcement
learning to solve online learning right.
So online learning is a use case where I do
not get I do not have the feedback available
to me a priori right, so the feedback keeps
coming piecemeal right so for example that
is a case where we are having news stories
that need to be shown to people that come
to my webpage right, and when people come
to the page I will have like some editors
will pick like 20 stories for me and from
those 20 stories I have to figure out which
are the ones I put up there prominently alright
and what is the feedback I am going to get.
Nobody tells me what stories that user is
going to like I mean then I cannot have a
supervised learning algorithm here right.
So the feedback I am going to get this if
the user clicks on the story I am going to
get a reward if the user does not click on
the story I will not get a reward that is,
essentially the feedback i am going to get
nobody tells me anything beforehand.
So I have to try out things I have to show
different stories to figure out which one
he is going to click on and I have very few
attempts to do this in so how do I do this
more effectively so, people have done a supervised
approach for solving this and it has worked
fairly successfully.
So it has worked fairly successfully but reinforcement
learning seems to be a much more you know
natural way of modeling these problems.
So not only in these kinds of a news story
selection people use reinforcement learning
ideas even in ad selection right, so how do
I see some of those ads that you see on the
sites when you go to Google or some other
page right so how are those ads selected so,
so there might be some very basic economic
criterion for selecting a slate of ads okay,
here are these 10 ads which would probably
give me the right payoff right and then you
can figure out which of those which three
of those 10 am I going to put here and things
like that you could use a reinforcement learning
solution for selecting those right.
Of course the this is this whole field called
computational advertising right, it is a lot
more complex than what I explained but RL
is a component in computational advertising
as well right.
okay here is the video courtesy Andrews webpage
the people recognize the guy there yeah, okay
this is not a human-sized helicopter but still
its a fairly large amazing ah all of this
is being learned by a RL agent this goes on
for a while we will stop.